黑客们好，欢迎观看高级漏洞利用模块的视频
hello hackers welcome to another video in the Advanced Exploitation Module
我们将讨论内存取证
we're going to be talking about memory forensics
基本就是
so really just the concept
内存里有用的东西在哪里
that hey once you know where something is in memory
哪里有能用于下一步行动的内存
where there's valid memory you can actually use that as a building block for your next steps
我们尝试围绕这一个概念
we're gonna try to cover one concept
就这一个主题
just that concept
在GDB中探索答案
crawl around in GDB a little
内容就这么多
and call it a day for the video
我们讨论的还是同一个多线程消息服务器
as a reminder we're still talking about the same threading message server
在这个服务中可以接入、留言、检索留言
where you can connect in leave messages retrieve messages
在单线程场景，它有安全地使用堆
and it uses the heap safely in a single threaded scenario
但在多线程场景中有问题
but with multiple threads problems occur
好吧
all right
再次提醒大家
and as a reminder again
在上集，我们泄露出了tcache_perthread_struct的地址
we in the last video leaked the address of actually the per thread struct
它位于进程里相关线程的arena中
which is in the thread specific arena of that process so
我把那个脚本整理了一下
I cleaned up that script a little bit
要指出几点
a couple of things I'll point out
一是我现在在GDB中启动服务进程
one is i am now launch the process in GDB
抱歉，我先启动进程，再用GDB附加到它
sorry I launch the process and then attached to it with GDB
这样方便我们进行内存取证
this is so that we can later do memory forensics
并在泄露出地址后探索内存
and crawl around memory when you leak some addresses
有几个问题
a couple of gotches
我先前，先建立连接，再附加进程，经常出问题
I have had very bad luck attaching with GDB after attaching over the network
gdb附加后会中断其它线程的read系统调用
that GDB attached tends to interrupt the read system call of whatever thread is reading
这导致了问题，所以我现在这样做
it causes havoc so what I tend to do now is
（口误）
I attaching GDB and I sorry
我先启动进程
I launched the process
用GDB附加进程
I attached GDB
gdb附加进程需要些时间
now this takes some time attaching GDB
它会中断程序，直到运行了这个continue
and then of course it interrupts the program and until this continue can run
脚本中可能存在竞争条件
you might have a race condition in your script
可能你尝试连接的进程正处于挂起状态
where you will try to connect to a process that is currently hung
它目前被gdb挂起
that's currently suspended by GDB and
为了解决它，我在这里加了个sleep
to get around that I have a sleep here all right
但攻击方式是一样的
so but the attack is the same
我在后台建立两个连接
I connect with two connections in the background
在一个线程中，发送1万次malloc和free
on one I send 10,000 allocation and free loops
在主线程中发送大量printf
in the other one, the main thread, I send a bunch of prints
然后展示结果
and then I read the the result
竞争条件发生在printf中
and of course we had that race condition in printf
通过它，泄露了指向tcache_perthread_struct的key指针
through which we leak out the key pointer back to the perthread struct in tcache
这样就完成了一个泄露
and with that we can get a leak so
我会展示一下这个泄露过程
I'm going to show you this leak
然后展示能通过泄露的地址挖掘出什么
and then show you what we can dig around for
这是GDP在启动
that's GDP starting up
这次失败了，没关系
and it failed this time that's fine
竞态条件并不能总成功
the race condition doesn't always succeed
成了，现在有了这个地址
boom so now we have a leak at this location
这应该是r1对应线程的tcache_perthread_struct
this is the per thread struct of most likely thread 1
因为是在这个循环中malloc的
because that's what's doing this looping
好吧，那我们能
all right so what can we
我们能从此通向何处
where can we go from there
好吧，当我们找到一个地址
all right the key thing is once we have one address
我们来到小白板前思考
we go back to drawing board and figure out
我们还能从中得到什么呢
what else can we get from that
要利用所有可用的信息
so use all of the information that's available
如果你有
if you have
现在你知道的是
right now what you know is
有个合法内存在这个指针指向的地址
there is valid memory at the page pointed to here
你还知道该内存页有写权限
you also know there's writable memory at that page
tcache_perthread_struct肯定是可写的
the per thread struct of course is writable
它要修改
it has to change
它有指向各个bin的指针等之类的变量
it has the pointers forward for the individual bins to the free allocations and so forth
它是可写的，而你现在知道了它的位置
it is writable and you now know where it is
而且你清楚这一整个内存页都是可写的
and you know that this whole page is full of writable memory
对，这很酷
right so that's very cool
有了这个地址，现在能在gdb中查看
given that you can now check in GDB for
当然
and of course
在调试器中，我们可以暂停攻击目标
we have the awesome capability of being able to stop what thing we're attacking in the debugger
但我们并非总能这样
you don't always have this capability
可能攻击的是个远程目标之类的
you might be attacking a remote target or whatever
但现在我们能查看这里还有什么
but we can actually check hey what else is there right
知道了它，是否能立马知道些其它地址
by knowing this address do we know any other addresses right away
有些地址间是有固定偏移量的
some addresses are at a constant offset
当知道了这些地址，又是否能立马知道些有用数据
and by knowing these addresses do we know the locations of interesting data
我们看个例子
so let's take a look for example
好的
all right
我们有了这个地址
so we have this address
tcache_perthread_struct的地址
this is the per thread struct
中断ult
let's break here
很简单，只需Ctrl C
simple just Ctrl C
info threads
有三个线程，都共享内存
we have three threads but they all share memory
我们来看一下
so let's just take a look
好吧
all right
这是我们刚刚泄露的地址
this is what we just leaked
它是这里某个线程的tcache_perthread_struct的地址
it is the per thread struct location of one of these threads
我们看看在这个内存页还有什么
let's take a look at what else is in that page
一个内存页有512个qwords（4k）
so page contains 512 qwords
把内存页的偏移清零
let's 0 out that page (offset)
这里有很多东西
boom a lot of stuff in that page
很多都是指向自身的指针
so a lot of it is pointers back to basically itself
这可能是另一种结构
so this is probably some some other structure
也许和arena有关，这是一些
maybe something to do with arena this is some
让我们看看
let's see
我还真不知道
I mean I honestly don't know
有一个
there is
我们要找到是一个有趣的不太一样的
what we're looking for is interesting looking things
这个看起来很有趣，对吧
this looks like an interesting thing right
我们要找到是
and of course what we're looking for here
还记的在arena元数据中（malloc_state）
as you recall in the thread metadata
有个指针能间接或直接指向main_arena（环形单链表）
all arenas have a pointer back to the main arena
我打赌这个指针在这
and here I bet is this pointer at this location
看一看
take a look
为啥它没解析出在libc中的符号
why is it not presolving the symbol in libc
总之，它是我们要找到。信我的
anyways that's what it is you'll have to take my word for it
如果我们
if we
稍等，我用另一种方式启动看看
I'll launch this a different way in a second to take a look
很奇怪，它竟然没解析出来
but it's really weird that it's not resolving the symbol
你要是用info proc map看一下
but if you look at info proc map
这个7f9d800
this 7 f 9 9 d 8 0
不，抱歉，这个 7f99dc5e
no sorry 7 f 9 9 d d c 5 e
7f99dc5e在这里，就在libc中
7 f 9 9 d d c 5 e is right here in libc
就在libc的最后一个映射中
in the last mapping of libc which is
我们换个方法看看
if we actually look at a different way
或者你装了能查看map的gdb插件
or if you have a GDB plugin installed that gives you permissions
libc的最后一个映射页 是可写的
the last mapping libc is writable
这肯定是main_arena的元数据
and this is of course the main arena metadata
我换种方式重启它
let me restart this in a different way
不在这里重启它了，而是
so instead of restarting it here we're just going to
我直接在gdb启动ult
I'm just gonna launch it ult in GDB here
运行
run
好
boom
竞争失败，重来
we lost the race let's restart it
好
boom
竞争成功
we won the race
好的，这是泄露的地址
all right here's the address
现在它指向8d0，而890就指向main_arena
now it goes to 8d0 and 890 is the main arena pointer
这并不令人意外
that isn't a surprise
稍等
wait
有东西在后台运行
something's running in the background
没
that wasn't okay
好吧
okay
我一直没启动这个
I never started this one
运行
run
攻击，竞争成功
attack win the race okay
当然了我们在GDB上，所以禁用了随机化
oh and of course we are on the GDB so it disabled randomization
我们看一下这里
so let's take a look here
0 好
0 boom
线程arena内存页到next指针的偏移量是890
oh sorry 890 was the offset
什么鬼
what the hell
就在我开始录制这个视频前
up until I started recording this video
GDB还在告诉我
GDB was happily telling me that
这是个main_arena指针
that's the main arena pointer
哦,抱歉
oh sorry
看到没，这是main_arena
there that's the main arena
好吧，之前的方式也能看到
okay and we'll of course see the same thing
看，这就是现场演示的诅咒
see this is the live demo curse
好了，我们开始
all right there we go
我们泄露了地址
we leaked the thing
我们重做一遍，暂停它
let's just redo this here okay kill it
这里是tcache_perthread_struct
here's the perthread struct
这里是  额
here is that main arena handler header thing metadata
线程arena的arena元数据中的一个指向main_arena的指针
the arena metadata for a thread arena with a pointer to the main arena
现在这个是main_arena
and here we go is the main arena
终于讲清了，酷
whoo okay cool
那么还有什么
so then what else
还有从这里到别处的已知偏移量吗
are there known offsets from here to other places in memory
现在我们知道了这个内存页
we again know this address or know this page
我们来看看
so let's see
还有其他的页面
there is other pages
这片内存大小是0x21000
so this guy is hex 2 1 0 0 0 in size
它们看起来像
they are look like
看起来他们是其它线程的
it looks like they are other
这是，我们看看
so this is let's see
这可能是第一个线程的栈
this is probably the stack of that first thread
这是第一个线程的堆
this is the heap of that first thread
准确的讲，它是一个堆区，主要给这个线程用
uh it's a heap region that was allocated for that thread's primary use
这是第二个线程的栈
this is the stack of the second thread
给第二个线程用的堆区
heap for the second thread
很明显，两者之间有一个固定偏移值
and it looks like obviously there is a constant offset between the two
所以仅通过泄露一个tcache_perthread_struct
so already we know where just by leaking one per thread pointer
就知道了所有线程的它的地址
we know where all the threads are
有到libc基址的固定偏移吗
is there a constant offset to libc
我们已经知道了一个libc中的地址
right we know the location of a libc pointer
但从中提取出libc基址有点困难
but it's a little tricky to extract that
我们可以，也会这样做
we can and we will
但我们先来确认一下
but let's first confirm that
它到libc的距离不是恒定的
the distance to libc is not constant
或者是恒定的
or it is constant
好吧，我觉得是
okay so I believe actually it is
是的，它当然是常数
yeah of course it is constant
知道了perthread_struct的地址，也就知道了libc的地址
so by knowing where the per thread struct is we also know where libc is
我们甚至不需要这个
so we don't even necessarily need this guy
这个偏移量，多次执行也不会变
we have this offset that will hold over multiple executions
好的，现在泄露出的地址变了
okay now we have a different address
和哦
and oops
偏移量会变
it doesn't hold
这是正确的
that's right
libc是映射到进程的
so libc is mapped
在这个映射过程中有一些抖动
there's some jitter that happens in this mapping
不是特别大的抖动
not a lot of jitter
事实上，这应该挺容易暴破
in fact probably that's easily bruteforceable
也可能是因为
it might also actually be the fact that
我们泄露的
we leaked
这里是怎么竞争的来着
how does that race condition work
会不会是我们泄漏错了
can we have leaked the wrong
我们再试第三次
let's try it again a third time
看看结果怎么样
and see what the result is
竞争失败了
that one failed
尝试第四次
let's try the fourth time
好吧
okay
这是tcache_perthread_struct的地址
that is the perthread struct
用第一个基址减它
Scrab the first
所以libc基址与泄露地址的偏移不是固定的
so there is jitter between the base of libc and the base of our thread struct
事实上偏移量变化不大
not a lot of jitter in fact
看起来最差的情况变的只有2字节
it looks like only really two bytes of jitter at worse
我们试个6万次
we tried this 60 000 times and
如果幸运的话，能试出来
and we eventually get lucky with an offset
现在我们知道了libc基址
now we know libc
现在我们有一定概率知道libc基址
so let's say for now we know libc with a probability though a libc address
一个相当高的概率
with a probability of fairly high right
或者说六万分之一
or one out of 60,000
看你对高的定义，它可以是高的
so depending on your definition of high this can be high
也可能不是
it might not be
好吧
all right
这对我们有什么帮助
how does that help us
当然，我们马上就能看到
of course right away we see that
因为这里有缓冲区溢出
because there's a buffer overflow here
知道libc基址，我们就能rop
knowing libc will allow us to rop
只要我们找出金丝雀
as soon as we find out the canary
我们还需要知道什么才能找到金丝雀
what else do we need to know to find the canary
我们需要知道
we need to know
比如，返回地址在哪里
where the return address is for example
我们需要一个，抱歉
we need a sorry
要在不破坏金丝雀的情况下溢出
to do the overflow and not trip the canary
我们需要知道金丝雀
we need to know the canary
这样能用原值覆盖它
so that we can write in the canary
或者我们要做一些其他的事，来跳过金丝雀
or we need to do some other thing to skip over the canary
所以不管怎样，重点是
so anyways the point is
我们已经大致知道libc在哪里
already we know where to some probability where libc is
我们知道了其他线程结构在哪里
we know where other thread structs are
我们知道了一个指向libc的指针的位置
and we know where a pointer to libc is
我们泄露了一个指向tcache_perthread_struct的指针
we have leaked a pointer to the per thread struct
在它前面一点，就是指向libc中main_arena的指针
and again a little before that is a pointer back to the main arena of libc
接下来我们要关注能通过它泄露出什么
so that is what then we can then focus on to leak next
这样我们就能百分百知晓libc基址
so that we know libc with complete certainty
所以我要在这里结束这个视频
so I'm going to end this video here
在下一集视频中，我们会搞清楚
in the next video we are going to figure out
当知道这个地址后，我们该如何动这里的值
how to get our hands on the value at this address when we know the address